<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>HUAT-RRR</title>
<link>https://.com/jclub.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://.com/jclub.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>RRR Resources</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.262</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Journal Club</title>
  <dc:creator>SGH PT Dept</dc:creator>
  <link>https://.com/jclub/journalclub/journalclub.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ <section id="session-31-aug-2021" class="level2"><h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-31-aug-2021">Session (31 Aug 2021)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>Messier et al</strong> Effect of High-Intensity Strength Training on Knee Pain and Knee Joint Compressive Forces Among Adults With Knee Osteoarthritis The START Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA 2021 Feb 16;325(7):646-657</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Read the <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2776330">abstract</a></p>
</section><section id="questions" class="level2"><h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="questions">Questions</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Is this a well-conducted study in terms of study design? (refer to Pointers)</li>
<li>Would you conclude that there is no difference between high vs low-intensity strength training? (refer to Pointers)
<ol type="a">
<li>in terms of self-reported knee pain</li>
<li>in terms of knee extensor strength</li>
<li>in terms of hip abductor strength</li>
<li>in terms of 6-minute walking distance</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>What are the mechanism of effects of high and low-intensity strength training? (read <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4663/9/2/32">Schoenfeld et al</a>)</li>
<li>What are the implications for clinical practice?</li>
<li>How would you have done the study differently? (Open Question)</li>
</ol></section><section id="designlink" class="level2"><h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="designlink">Study Design</h2>
<p>Methods/procedures used by the researchers to reduce/minimize study bias</p>
<section id="recruitment" class="level3"><h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recruitment">Recruitment</h3>
<p><em>Participants were not aware of the hypotheses tested</em>. What are the implications?</p>
</section><section id="randomization" class="level3"><h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="randomization">Randomization</h3>
<p>How does randomization reduce confounding? (<strong>Confounding</strong> Chapter)</p>
<p>Why was randomization stratified by sex and baseline BMI?(<strong>Confounding</strong> Chapter)</p>
</section><section id="analysis" class="level3"><h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis">Analysis</h3>
<p>Participants were analyzed according to their assigned randomization group <em>even if they were nonadherent to their assigned intervention</em> (<strong>Confounding</strong> Chapter)</p>
<p>Analysis were <em>adjusted for sex, baseline BMI, and baseline outcome values</em> (<strong>Regression</strong> Chapter on ANCOVA)</p>
</section></section><section id="findingslink" class="level2"><h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="findingslink">Findings</h2>
<p>Interpret the RCT findings by quantifying the evidence for/against a treatment effect Association = Treatment Effect = Treatment Difference</p>
<div class="l-body">
<table class="table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 32%">
<col style="width: 67%">
</colgroup>
<thead><tr class="header">
<th>Findings</th>
<th>Interpretation</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>P&lt;0.05</td>
<td>Evidence of a (non-zero) treatment difference/effect</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>P&gt;0.05</td>
<td>Insufficient/No evidence of association (≠ evidence of no treatment difference)<sup>1</sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>(1) P&lt;0.05; 95% CIs exclude trivial effects</td>
<td>Evidence of a clinically meaningful treatment difference</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>(2) P&lt;0.05; 95% CIs exclude meaningful effects</td>
<td>Evidence of a treatment diff; however, this difference is not clinically meaningful</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>(3) P&lt;0.05; 95% CIs include trivial + meaningful effects</td>
<td>Cannot exclude non-clinically meaningful treatment difference</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>(4) P&gt;0.05; 95% CIs exclude meaningful effects</td>
<td>(Possibly) Evidence of no treatment difference</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>(5) P&gt;0.05; 95% CI limits include meaningful effects</td>
<td>CI indicates a wide range of plausible true treatment differences (inconclusive finding as all scenarios are possible)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>(6) P&gt;0.05; 95% CI limits include trivial + meaningful effects</td>
<td>No evidence of treatment difference, however, we cannot exclude clinically important difference</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
<p>We are assuming that the 95%CI represent the range of plausible values for the true (hidden) treatment effects. This is, strictly speaking, untrue<sup>2</sup> (<strong>General Overview</strong> Chapter).</p>


</section><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Beware of making the “Absence of Evidence is NOT Evidence of Absence” fallacy↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>More accurately, but less comprehensibly, the 95%CI is the range of values computed using a method such that over multiple study replications with a 95% CI computed in each replication, 95% of the intervals would contain the true treatment effect.↩︎</p></li>
</ol></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>p-values</category>
  <category>confidence interval</category>
  <category>RCT</category>
  <category>confounding</category>
  <guid>https://.com/jclub/journalclub/journalclub.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://.com/jclub/journalclub/jama.JPG" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Intervention Evaluation</title>
  <dc:creator>SGH PT Dept</dc:creator>
  <link>https://.com/jclub/rx_eval/rx_eval.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="background-knowledge" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background-knowledge">Background Knowledge</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Confounding by treatment indication</p></li>
<li><p>Regression analyses and covariate adjustment</p></li>
<li><p>P-values and CI interpretation</p></li>
</ul>
<aside>
Don’t freak out if you don’t understand them well. Get more information from the <code>Workshop</code> section
</aside>
</section>
<section id="propensity-score-adjustment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="propensity-score-adjustment">Propensity Score Adjustment</h2>
<style>
div.blue { background-color:#e6f0ff; border-radius: 0px; padding: 0px;}
</style>
<div class="blue">
<p>Excellent tutorial (with helpful audio narration!) by Prof Frank Harrell can be found <a href="http://hbiostat.org/bbr/md/propensity.html">here</a></p>
</div>
<section id="high-level-summary" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="high-level-summary">High-level summary</h3>
<ul>
<li>Propensity score (PS) analysis is a regression-based method that adjusts the treatment effects for many (<em>known</em>) confounders</li>
<li>PS analysis is used when (i) you need to aggressively adjust the treatment effects for multiple confounders and (ii) the outcome model does not allow multiple variables to be reliably fitted. Thus, PS analysis allows aggressive confounder adjustment <strong>without</strong> increasing the risk of model overfitting</li>
<li>To summarize the confounding information into a single number, a propensity model is created by regressing the treatment status on all the confounders. In that model, the PS is the estimated (conditional) probability of getting treatment B vs.&nbsp;treatment A given a set of (observed/measured) confounding variables.</li>
<li>Researchers would often use the PS to assess whether they could achieve balance between the treatment groups on the confounders.</li>
<li>After computing the PS, a multivariable outcome model is fitted to estimate the treatment effects. In the outcome model, the PS is simply treated as a covariate. PS adjustment “works” when <strong>all</strong> relevant variables (important prognostic factors) are included in the propensity model.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="example" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="example">Example</h3>
<p><a href="https://thejns.org/spine/view/journals/j-neurosurg-spine/23/5/article-p558.xml?tab_body=fulltext">Gornet et al JNS 2015</a></p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>To adjust for any possible effects of demographic characteristics or preoperative measures on clinical outcomes, the propensity score technique was used. The propensity score was calculated based on a logistic regression model with the following covariates: age, height, weight, sex, race, marital status, education level, work status, workers’ compensation, spinal litigation, tobacco use, alcohol use, nonnarcotic pain medication use, weak narcotic pain medication use, strong narcotic pain medication use, muscle relaxant medication use, time to onset of symptoms, and previous neck surgery, as well as treatment level and preoperative scores for NDI, 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36) Physical Component Summary (PCS), SF-36 Mental Component Summary (MCS), neck pain, arm pain, gait, foraminal compression test reaction, and neurological status (motor function, sensory, and reflex). Where an observation was missing for a given demographic/pre-operative variable in a particular patient, the mean value of the corresponding treatment group was imputed for the missing data point. Covariate balance after propensity score adjustment was examined using ANCOVA or logistic regression.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
</section>
<section id="bayesian-inference" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bayesian-inference">Bayesian Inference</h2>
<ul>
<li>Go to “Overview” chapter (Workshop section)</li>
</ul>
<section id="example-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="example-1">Example</h3>
<p><a href="https://thejns.org/spine/view/journals/j-neurosurg-spine/23/5/article-p558.xml?tab_body=fulltext">Gornet et al JNS 2015</a></p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In the Frequentist approach, evidence for efficacy is generally thought to be provided by p ≤ 0.05. This is the probability of observing, over repetitions of the same experiment, a test statistic as impressive as or more impressive than the observed statistic for comparing 2 groups if the null hypothesis is true. Bayesian results are “positive,” by comparison, when, for example, the posterior probability of efficacy is ≥ 0.95. For assessing evidence, the Bayesian posterior probability of a statement such as “Treatment 1 tends to be better than Treatment 2” is the probability that the statement is true. In addition, the 95% Bayesian credible intervals are provided for parameters of interest. The primary objective in this study was to show that the overall success rate in the investigational group was statistically noninferior to the rate in the historical control group.</p>
</blockquote>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>confounder</category>
  <category>regression</category>
  <category>Bayesian</category>
  <category>propensity score</category>
  <guid>https://.com/jclub/rx_eval/rx_eval.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://.com/jclub/rx_eval/rx1.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="111" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Articles 2023</title>
  <dc:creator>SGH PT Dept</dc:creator>
  <link>https://.com/jclub/articles2023/articles_2023.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ <section id="rct-paper" class="level2"><h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rct-paper">RCT paper</h2>
<p>The Group has chosen <a href="https://jnnp.bmj.com/content/78/7/678.long">JNNP 2007 Asburn et al</a></p>
<section id="plus-points" class="level3"><h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plus-points">Plus Points</h3>
<ul>
<li>The authors adjusted for baseline SAS and previous history of falls (to “level the playing field” for both groups)</li>
</ul></section><section id="minus-points" class="level3"><h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minus-points">Minus Points</h3>
<ul>
<li>Table 3: It is shame that readers are only given P-values to guide their interpretation of the regression results. Also, notice that <strong>unadjusted</strong> difference in proportions are given. Hence, it is possible to observe an unadjusted 95%CI that includes 0 but a P-value that is &lt;0.05<br>
</li>
<li>Separate regression analysis done at each timepoint: bias from non-random missing observations may creep into results <sup>1</sup>
</li>
</ul></section><section id="practice" class="level3"><h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice">Practice</h3>
<ul>
<li>Table 4: The authors sensibly provided adjusted difference. Try interpreting them.</li>
</ul></section><section id="interesting" class="level3"><h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="interesting">Interesting</h3>
<ul>
<li>If we have the time and energy, we could compute ORs by hand (or software)</li>
</ul>


</section></section><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Certainly a forgivable sin given the limited availability of software to handle more complex models in 2007↩︎</p></li>
</ol></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>p-values</category>
  <category>confidence interval</category>
  <category>RCT</category>
  <category>confounding</category>
  <category>research design</category>
  <guid>https://.com/jclub/articles2023/articles_2023.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://.com/jclub/articles2023/a2023.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
